<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A relation made in the House of Commons by Col. Nathaniel Fiennes concerning the surrender of the city and castle of Bristoll, August 5. 1643 together with the transcripts and extracts of certain letters wherein his care for the preservation of the city doth appear.</title>
            <author>Fiennes, Nathaniel, 1607 or 8-1669.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B22950</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12037821</idno>
  <idno type="VID">196872</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248520319</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing F876</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12037821</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B22950)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 196872)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 239:E64, no 12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A relation made in the House of Commons by Col. Nathaniel Fiennes concerning the surrender of the city and castle of Bristoll, August 5. 1643 together with the transcripts and extracts of certain letters wherein his care for the preservation of the city doth appear.</title>
                  <author>Fiennes, Nathaniel, 1607 or 8-1669.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R.D.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1643].</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Thomason Collection, British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Bristol (England) --  History --  Siege, 1643.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:196872:1"/>
            <p>A RELATION MADE In the House of Commons, BY Col: <hi>Nathaniel Fiennes,</hi> CONCERNING The Surrender of the City and Castle OF BRISTOLL, <hi>August</hi> 5. 1643.</p>
            <p>Together with the Transcripts and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts of certain Letters, wherein his care for the preservation of the City doth appear.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license" subtype="imprimatur">
                        <p>
                           <hi>Imprimatur,</hi> JOHN WHITE.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>London, Printed for <hi>R. D.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="statement">
            <pb facs="tcp:196872:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:196872:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Mr. <hi>SPEAKER,</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough both my selfe and the whole Kingdome have cause to be humbled under the hand of God, which hath lighted heavy upon us, in the late unhappy defeat of Sir <hi>William Wallers</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my neer the <hi>Devises,</hi> and in consequence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, in the losse of a place of such importance as is the City of <hi>Bristoll,</hi> yet I make no doubt but I shall give cleere satisfaction both to this House, and to the whole world; That though I have great cause to be griev'd at the successe, yet I have no cause at all to be ashamed for any mis-carriage in the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of my duty and trust, having performed it to the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most of my power, and beyond what could be expected from me, considering the condition wherein I was, and in this great unhappines wch hath befallen my self and the whole kingdom; it is some ease to me that I have opportunity to cleere my selfe in this place, from such aspersions as most unworthily and most un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justly have been layed upon me, by those that have condemned me before they heard me, or any other upon whose relation they were able to found a right judgement concerning the carriage of this unhappy businesse.</p>
            <p>Sir, I wil not trouble you with rehearsing the occasiō of my first undertaking the care &amp; charge of the City, nor with the dangers &amp; difficulties that I have gone through in the managing thereof: only thus much I shall say, that as I little enjoyed my self in the employment, having no rest or quiet from continuall care and paines, so I never did affect it, but allwayes declined it, and that not in a way of complement, but really as my private Letters to my Lord Generall, my father, and others, and my expressions at severall times to my friends in private, may witnesse; and the reason why I did desire to be taken off that imployment, was this: Because I knew that the place was of very great impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to the Kingdom, and the losse thereof would much reflect upon him that had the charge thereof, though he were not at all in any fault, having not sufficient means to defend it, which I alwayes feared would be the destiny of that place (as it hath been) by reason that it would require a great Garrison, and charge to maintain it, which I found would not so soone and so
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:196872:3"/> easily be setled, but that some misfortune was like to befall it (as it hath done) in the mean time. Notwithstanding, seeing God was pleased to pitch me there, and that I could not get off this service, (although I earnestly endeavoured it) I bethought my selfe, how I might put the place into a posture of defence, and though it be one of the hardest towns in <hi>England</hi> to be fortified, yet by Gods assistance I drew Fortifications round about it, and had almost brought them to perfection: and knowing that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out men, arms, and ammunition, all that I had done would be but like a body without a soul, and considering how hard a thing it would be to have men and maintenance continually from <hi>London,</hi> for the defence of that City; and that it was as impossible (what conceits soever some had of the wealth of that City) to maintaine the Garrison, out of the City, without the assistance of the adja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Counties: I made certain Propositions soon after my first coming thither, to the Gentlemen of the adjacent counties, for the setling and maintaining of a sufficient Garrison there; which (at length, I got most of the Gentlemen to consent unto, as may appear by Certificates under their hands:) After I sent them to my Lo: Generall, who liked them very well, and wrote a Letter to my father, wherein he did earnestly presse him to move the Committee for the safety, and the Houses for to settle the Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son according to those Propositions; accordingly the Committee and the Houses were moved in it: an Ordinance framed to that purpose, and Committee appointed to consider of it, and to bring, it to perfection: and there was never a Post, but I wrote, earnestly for the expediting of it, and pressed it, as that which imported no lesse then the safety of the City: (all this my Letters to my Lord, Father, and others can testifie) yet I know not what obstructions it met with at the Committee, but I am very confident had it been dispatched when I first sent about it, before the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies had fallen into the countries round about that City, it had not been in the hands that now it is. In the mean time I did not faile to use all the care I could, and all the power I had to streng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then that Garrison with men, arms, and ammunition; for where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as I found, there only Colonell <hi>Essex's</hi> and Col. <hi>Pophams</hi> Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: Sir <hi>William Waller</hi> drew out, Col. <hi>Essexs</hi> Regiment, and all the Troops of horse that were in it, except two for the service of the field, in stead whereof, I raised and armed as many troops as he drew forth: and without any money allowed from <hi>London</hi> rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:196872:3"/> armed and coated a Regiment of foot, of 1200. men. After that, when Sir <hi>Ralph Hoptons</hi> Army, upon the defeat of the Earl of <hi>Stamford,</hi> began to draw down towards Sommersetshire, and Marquesse <hi>Hartford,</hi> and Prince <hi>Maurice,</hi> endeavoured to joyne their forces with him: Six Companies of Col. <hi>Pophams</hi> Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were drawn forth to ioyn with the forces of Sommerset to prevent the joyning of the enemies western forces; but these were routed, and lost all their arms at <hi>Wells.</hi> After that, when Sir <hi>Wil. Waller</hi> came from <hi>Woster,</hi> and had his Randevouz at <hi>Bath,</hi> both he and Sir <hi>Arthur Hazelrig,</hi> and all the Gentlemen of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try were very earnest with me to afford him a good strength of foot to his horse, whereby he might be inabled to encounter with the enemy, and be master of the field, which was pressed upon me both by him, and others with great earnestnesse, as the onely means to preserve <hi>Bristoll</hi> and the west of <hi>England,</hi> (as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by a Letter signed by him and sir <hi>Arthur Hazelrig,</hi> (which <hi>I</hi> shall desire may be read:) Hereupon I advised with my Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and concluded that if there had been a sufficient Garrison within the City, whereby it might have subsisted of it selfe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the help of an Army in the field, that it would not have bin wisdom in me to suffer so considerable a place to depend upon the fortune of an Army in the field; but seeing there was not a sufficient Garrison established in the town, but that the enemy being master of the field, would in a short time be master of the City also: it was held the best way to make Sir <hi>Wil: Wallers</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my as strong as possible I could; and seeing the security of the City was to depend upon the successe of his Army, to use all means that might any wayes contribute towards the good suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse thereof; and so I resolved to send him 1200. men out of the towne, which accordingly I did, besides my Regiment of horse, which was with him before: After expressing that I was forced to cast <hi>Bristoll,</hi> and the fortune thereof upon the successe of that Army; But when all Sir <hi>Will. Wallers</hi> Army was routed, and amongst them those 1200. that I had sent out of <hi>Bristoll</hi> were all dispersed, and had lost all their arms; Every body loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked upon <hi>Bristoll</hi> as a lost town, and that onely with respect to the western Army, without relation to those forces which came from <hi>Oxford</hi> with Prince <hi>Rupert,</hi> (which were more then the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:) Hereupon Sir <hi>Wil: Waller</hi> resolved to retire with his horse (wherein he did wisely, for otherwise he would have lost those
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:196872:4"/> that remained of them, to no purpose;) and Sir ARTHUR HAZELRIGGE and Colonell BORRGHELL though sorely wounded, and divers Gentlemen that had formerly resided constantly in <hi>Bristoll,</hi> thought fit to withdraw themselve, which I do not speak to any other purpose (many of them having no tye at all to that place) but onely to shew that it was the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner I apprehension of these men, that <hi>Bristoll</hi> was lost when Sir <hi>William Waller</hi> lost the field, and that they did not hold that either Town or Castle was tenable (for that to my knowledge they might have had lodgings in either) all which I am enforced to declare, to satisfie the world, that there were some besides my self and the Councell of War at <hi>Bristoll,</hi> that were of opinion, that neither the Town nor Castle were tenable against such For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as came against them. Notwithstanding all this, and that I had but 700 men left in the town, and not a penny of money left to pay th<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m, much lesse to raise or arm any more, yet I was not wholly discouraged, but it pleasing God to stir up the heart of Sir <hi>John Horner,</hi> (who hath carryed himself very nobly in this bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sinesse to the end) and some other honest men to lend me some money, (whom I am confident you will never suffer to be Loser, for the testifying of their affection in such a time of extremity;) by this means I was encouraged to try what strength of Foot <hi>I</hi> could adde to these I had already, and resolved to make use of the Arms of the Trained-<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ands of the City, which I did, and by that mean, and by ready money, I procured about One thousand or Eleven hundred Arms, and raised so many men in Five dayes space; which time of respite the Enemy gave me, staying til the <hi>Oxford</hi> Army under the Conduct of Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> came up on <hi>Glocestershire</hi> side the Town. Having gotten together between Seventeen hundred, or Eighteen hundred men (which was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for the manning of those Works, that required at least twice as many) I resolved to make the best defence I could, and as long as I could, although when I saw the two Armies drawn upon both sides the town (being as I have been firce informed. Fifteen Regiments of Foot, and Twelve Regiments of Horse) I did know, that without a miracle, it was impossible the town should be maintained against them for one week, yet neither the sight of their great Army, nor their short Summons, did cause us to surrender the place, as some have reported we did; and the Enemy expected we should have done (as some of them
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:196872:4"/> have expressed since the rendring of the town) but we stood it out Four dayes together, wherein they spared not to plye us with small and great shot, and with their Granadoes, giving our men (who were forced to be constantly all of them upon duty, and were so Five dayes and nights together) no rest at all, and two sharp assaults they made upon us, the one on Munday was seven-night at midnight, at which time having given a signall by three peeces of Ordnance shot off, first on the one side of the water, and then answered by as many on the otherside, they fell on very desperately on both sides the town at once, but were beaten off with losse; whereupon on Tuesday they entred into a solemn debate, whether they should proceed to fall upon the town by way of Assault, or by way of Approach; and it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved, that it should be by way of Assault, as may appear by the Result of their Councell of War (which we found in the pocket of Colonell <hi>Buck</hi> (who, with divers other Officers and Gentlemen of quality was slain in that Assault) and accordingly on VVednesday morning at break of the day they made a most furious Assault upon all sides of the town in Eight or Nine places at once, with Fire-Pikes and Granadoes in their hands, and with VVains full of Faggots, which they drove into the Ditch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, that first getting upon them, they might after get over the works, and they ran on so desperately, that they got up to the portalls of the Canon, and to the Pallisadoes of the Forts, and would not give over till they were knock'd down with Stones and Halberts, and so with the losse of divers hundreds of their men, (with many Officers and Gentlemen of quality) besides a multitude that were wounded and maimed, they were beaten off on all sides, and the ground bestrewed with their dead bodies in all places where they stormed.</p>
            <p>But in one place where the works were not quite perfected, the Ditch being not made without side, nor the Foot Bank with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in side the work, they entred the line, there being but a weake Guard in that place, yet as I did in all places where through the want of foot I could not place a Guard strong enough, there were neer a 100. horse under the command of Major <hi>Langrishe,</hi> appointed to second the Foot there, who were commanded to charge the enemy so soon as they should enter, but these horse did not charge the enemy as they were commanded, though some of them were most earnestly entreated thereunto by my
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:196872:5"/> Lieutenant Colonell, who had the command of that part; when the enemy first began to enter, and our men began to give back; so the enemy falling on in five distinct bodies, the first and the second got over, and presently got to the walls and places of advantage within the line, but as the third body was entring, my troop of horse, that was set to second another Guard, hearing of the enemies entrie in this place, came down and fell upon the third Devision of the enemy as they were entring, and cut them off; but being assaulted both by those that were entring, and those that had entered, before they came down firing upon them from the walls (which they had got the advantage of) they were forced to retreat, and then the enemy had free liberty to possesse themselves of the Suburbs by the Colledge Green, and Froom-gate, which they did, and hoping to force their entrie by that gate, they drew off the whole body of their forces to the place; whereupon we also drew off all our men from off the line into the town, and not staying till they came to the Gates, we o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened them, and issued forth upon the enemy both with horse and foot, and beat them back from street to street for an houre and halfe together, insomuch that many of them threw downe their arms and cryed for Quarter, but the enemy drawing down fresh Companies still one after another upon us, and we being not able to answer them in the like kind, having so few men as we had, our men were forced at length to retreat into the town, and then, and not till then, whether it were out of extream wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinesse, (having bin upon continuall duty for five nights together) or that they began to be disheartned, the souldiers began to drop away from their colours, and from their guards, insomuch that (having declared that all souldiers should repair into the Marsh unto their colours, and that there they should receive both vict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ualls and mony:) when I went into the Marshe to see what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany came together, of 12. or 14. Companies there came not a 100. men, and yet the enemy drew down thick upon the back; and it began now to be low water in the <hi>Key,</hi> so that they might wade over at their pleasure, and the guards being so weak, might (if they had attempted it) have forced their entrie into the town in halfe an hour: Hereupon I resolved to call a Counsell of war, for that now was the time that either we must treat or retreat into the Castle, if it should be thought fit so to do, for that the Town could not be kept any longer.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:196872:5"/>
            <p>The Officers of the Garison being gathered together, and also the Gentlemen of the adjacent Counties, Sir <hi>Iohn Horner, Edward Sironde,</hi> Mr. <hi>Stevens,</hi> &amp;c. We tooke it into consideration, whether we should treate with the enemy or no, or retreat into the Castle, firing the Town behind, as we made our retreat, if wee could keep the Town no longer, every body seemed to be of opinion, and as for the retiring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Castle before we treated with the enemy, these considerations were offered against it. First, all our Horse, which were 300. All the Souldiers that could not be contained in the Castle (which would have been near halfe of them) all our friends, both Citizens, and those that had retired themselves into <hi>Bristol</hi> out of the adjacent Counties, excepting some few Principall men, must have been sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed to the furie of the enemy, the Citie was like in great part to be put into ashes, and those that should retire into the Castle (if they were not prevented by the enemie) falling upon them on one hand, and the generality of the City on the other, (as I am credibly infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, there was such a designe) they must also within three or foure daies have been the objects of the enemies cruelty and revenge (who would have given them no conditions) when they had no further re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat to make conditions in.</p>
            <p>A second consideration was this, that if we did fall upon these desperate resolutions, we should destroy, only that we might destroy without any hope of defending the place above three or foure daies, and without expectation of any relief in three or foure weeks, (nay it is clear, we should not have had any in sixe or eight weeks. That which made it evident, that wee could not hold the Castle above two or three daies, was because we had not amunition for a longer time, having only fifty barrells of Powder, and no match at all, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the proportion of powder that we had spent the daies before, this would not have served us above two daies: And if any blame me for being no better provided with Ammunition, my Answer is, that I found but 45. Barrels of powder in the Town when I first entred upon the charge thereof, that I had set all the men I could find a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the City, and in the Countrie thereabouts, to make Salt Pet<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r and Powder, that I had severall times searched all the Ships and Shops in the City, and had brought into the store all the Powder and Match that could be found, that I had sent to <hi>London</hi> often for Powder, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring that want of Powder and men would be the losse of that Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and of the <hi>West</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> that I received only 30. Barrels of Powder from <hi>London,</hi> and that 70. more vvere sent by a Ship (which
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:196872:6"/> as I understand since is cast away) that unlesse I had taken care for more surety to have some from <hi>France</hi> (from whence I had 126 bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels) long ere this both the Town and Sir <hi>William Waller</hi> had bin lost for want of powder, &amp; I was forced to help Sir <hi>William Waller</hi> with so great a proportion of powder, (about 60 barrels) and so much match, before the Siege of the City, that I could not recover it, the enemy gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving meno time to furnish my self again with match and powder, and if I had not helped Sir <hi>VVilliam VValler</hi> at that time, he having but 6 barrels of powder left him after the fight at <hi>Launsdown:</hi> both the losse of his Army and of the City in consequence thereof, would have been imputed to me, and as I said before, I held the security of <hi>Bristoll,</hi> to be involved in the security of that Army, and that the destiny of the one, would bee the fall of the other. Besides whatever opinion some may have of the strength of the Castle (and indeed I had a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter opinion of it my selfe, till I saw the manner of the Enemies stor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming and the execution that their peices of batterie did eaven upon our perapets of Earth) I am of the opinion that the enemy was, that they would by battery and storme of hand have entred the Castle in two dayes and so they did resolve to have stormed it, being provided with close decked boates and galleries to that purpose; and I doe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily believe that they would have gained it though with the losse of some men, whereof there would have been after, a great deale more losse and massacre on every side, when they should have entred in that manner by force, which I am confident in the eye of any judicious man, they would have done, the fortifications about the Castle being not perfected as they vvere intended, upon these Reasons it was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded by the Counsell of War that we should rather treat, &amp; accept of conditions which might preserve the City to the <hi>Kingdom</hi> and 300 horse and 1500 Foot to the Parliament, besides the lives and estates of many friends to the Parliament; then to expose al these to evident ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine and destruction for to preserve the Castle 2 or 3 daies vvithout hope of keeping it longer: and vvithout hope of having reliefe in that space, or in any time it could be imagined the Castle could be kept, though we could have kept it 2 mon. as I verily perswade my self we could not have kept it a daies. When vve novv entred into the Parley, all the conditions that vve desired all most vve had accorded unto us, excepting that of the Ammunition, Souldiers marching out vvith his armes and colours vvheron I intended to have insisted and should have done it, but that vvhilst I vvas vvithdravvne to debate it, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with my Officers. divers of my Captaines, came in and told me,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:196872:6"/> that doe what they could, they could not get together above six a piece of their compainies that many of them did run over the water to the enemy, which not onely shewed the enemy that our men were disheartened, and that they should find but slender opposition, but it also shewed the enemy how they might with ease come over the water into the tovvne; vvhich undoubtedly, they vvould have done, vvithall the ease that might bee, had vve broke off the Treaty vvithout comming to an agreement. It is true, conditions vvere not observed (vvhich turned very much to the prejudice of the State) for by that meanes they ruined a Regiment of three hundred horse and disperced a body of 1200, or 1500 Foot, vvhich if faith had beene kept; I vvould have brought in a body together to this City, and that was a speciall thing that induced me to surrender upon Conditions, esteeming that the preservation of so many Horse and Foot, for the serving the State, together with the lives and Estates of divers hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of our Friends, was of more consideration unto the Parliament, then the desperate holding out of a Castle for a few dayes to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose but the distruction of those that could not bee drawne into it first, and of all those also that were drawne into it afterwards there being no hope of any timely reliefe, but it is time that the falshood of the Enemy (against which there is no Fence) hath in great part de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived us of the fruit of our conditions dismounting our Troopers pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laging our Souldiers as well Officers as others and by threats and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticements drawing off our Souldiers to serve them, or dispercing them into their severall Countries, and our convoy used us worst of all, pillaging us all most all the way they went with us, and extorting moneyes from us, wherein the Officers for the most part were as much to blame as the Common-Souldiers, yet I must doe this right to the Princes, Prince <hi>Rupert,</hi> and Prince <hi>Maurice,</hi> contrary to what I find in a printed pamphlet, that they were so farre from sitting upon their horses, triumphing and rejoycing at these disorders that they did ride amongst these plunderers with their swords, hacking and slashing them, and Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> did excuse it to me in a very faire way and with expressions as if he were much troubled at it:</p>
            <p>One thing more I shall endeavour to give you satisfaction in and so I shall conclude. It is concerning Sir <hi>William Wallers</hi> leaving of <hi>Bristoll,</hi> which by something that I have seen in Print, as the resolution of a Councell of warre held at <hi>Bristoll,</hi> is sayed to have been by the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of mee, and my Officers, at which Councell of Warre, neither I nor any of my Officers were present, nor doe I know that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:196872:7"/> Sir <hi>VVilliam VValler</hi> was ever importuned, or so much as moved by mee, or any of my Officers to goe from thence, but finding by many expressions of his that hee did not intend to bee besieged with his Horse in that Towne (as it would not have been wisedome for him to have been) the first Speech that I had with him about his stay or departure, was when he drew out his Horse upon <hi>Bundam Downe,</hi> neere <hi>Bristoll,</hi> for to take a view of them, at which time I asked him if the Enemy should advance towards <hi>Bristoll,</hi> how he would dispose of himself and his Horse, whereunto he answered that he must retreat, and thereupon so so<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n as I come off the Downe, I called a Councell of Warre, and acquainted them with Sir <hi>VVilliam VVallers</hi> resoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and thereupon we made certaine propositions unto him, that if he did leave the Towne, t<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at hee would leave a certain proportion of Horse with us (which was my Regiment) and that hee would leave all his foot with us, who if vvee could get Arms for them, might be some help to us, which proposition he stuck at a while, alleadging that he would take the field againe, and would have his Foot with him, but after he was contented to leave the Foot with us, finding it was not possible for him to keepe the field with a fevv unarmed Foot, and a many scattred and disheartned Troopes, which I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent did not altogether make 500. Horse when he left <hi>Bristoll,</hi> yet they were two many to lose, as I am confident they would all have been lost had they stayed in <hi>Bristoll,</hi> or have runne away to the Enemy, as many of them did, and they would have beene of no use to us for the Defence of the Citie, but have helped to have spent our Provisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and disturbed the Citie quarrelling continually with the Towns<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men for want of Money to pay their quarters (as they did) and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was my opinion and is still that it was best for the advantage of the service that Sir <hi>Villiam VValler</hi> should draw them out of the Town, and this I might expressein discourse, but that I ever moved Sir <hi>VVil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam VValler</hi> thereunto, much lesse importuned him. I doe not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, onely just as he was going to take Horse, he desired me, if it was my opinion, that I would set it under my hands, that I did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of his resolution therein, which accordingly I did, but I knew nothing of his going to my Lord Generall, but expected rather that he would have gone to <hi>Gloster</hi> or <hi>Exeter,</hi> and gathered a Body there, to have afforded me some speedy reliefe, which when he went from me, he told me he would doe, and that he would not be long ere he retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to my reliefe, or to that purpose, and as it appeareth by a Letter, which he writ to my Lord Generall, the day after he came to <hi>Bristoll,</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:196872:7"/> that he intended not to stay there, but to take the Field againe, so it did appeare to me by many of his expressions, that he never intended to bee kept up in <hi>Bristoll,</hi> and I never heard that he advised with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny or my Officers concerning his stay at <hi>Bristoll,</hi> but supposing that he must not stay in the Towne, hee advised with one of my Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, whether he had best to retire to <hi>Gloster,</hi> or to <hi>Exeter,</hi> who advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Him to goe for <hi>Exeter,</hi> and to take <hi>Do<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>chester</hi> in the way, and so gathering all the Forces he could to joine with the Earle of <hi>VVarwick,</hi> to raise the siege of <hi>Exeter,</hi> and after to make a Body to releeve us, which in my opinion had been no ill course if it had been followed. Thus having declared unto you all particulars at large, I desire you would be pleased to let the truth of what I have affirmed be exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at a Councell of Warre, that I may bee cleared or condemned ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as they shall finde the truth or falshood of what I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>The Copy of a Letter written to my Lord <hi>Say,</hi> by Colonell <hi>Nathaniel Fiennes,</hi> and the Gentlemen of <hi>Sommer set</hi> and <hi>Glocester-shire</hi> for the setling of a sufficient Garison in that <hi>City;</hi> they having written another to my Lord Generall to the same purpose.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it please your Lordship,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>TO Understand first the importance of this City of <hi>Bristoll,</hi> and next the condition in which we are left to defend it: The enemy hath lately cast his eye upon it, prompted by the witty malice of our Malignants, to espy his advantage, if he possesse this City, hee will reape these benefits by our losse. 1. he will get much money, Armes and Amunition in a more cheape and lesse hazardous way, then he can have them out of the Low-Countreyes, all which hee will pay for with monopolies and ingrossments of Trade, (things with which the great ones of this Towne have bin well acquainted, and are ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore malignant. 2. If he gaine this Town he will soone subdue <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester,</hi> and become Master of all the Tract betweene <hi>Shrewsbury,</hi> and and the <hi>Lizards</hi> point in <hi>Cornwall,</hi> a quarter so plentifull as his plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering army yet never saw. 3. He will become master of all the Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficke of that Inland Sea the Severne, and make all the Shipping both of the <hi>VVelch,</hi> and <hi>English</hi> Coasts his owne. 4. His Neighbourhood to Wales: will from time to time supply him with a body of Foot 5. We shall lose a Port Towne very important for the service of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and fit to give Landing to the Rebels of that place or any other Enemy.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:196872:8"/>
            <p>The diseased state we stand in followeth.</p>
            <p>The Enemy hath lately bin before our doores invited by a treach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erous party in this Town: we had then 2 Regiments of foot, Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell <hi>Essexes,</hi> and Col. <hi>Pophams,</hi> and almost a whole Regiment of horse, yet the extent of this scattering City, commanded by many Hils, and the conspiring multitude within it enforced all our men at once to doe duty: so that we had bin undone by watching over our safety, if the enemy had bin able to persist, since which time Sir <hi>William Waller</hi> hath beene with us, (and being desirous to take the field) hath taken from us Col. <hi>Eslex</hi> whole Regiment of foot, and the most part of our horse. And though we acknowledge a partie in the Field, to bee a good strength to us, yet wee conceive a City of this consequence ought to have an inward strength of his owne, and not to depend wholly upon the uncertaine issue of warre abroad; considering how apt the Town is to rise against us if the dye of war should turn against Sir <hi>William Waller,</hi> and the enemy pursue his victory to the Walls or if a joint party from <hi>Cornwall</hi> and <hi>VVales,</hi> should passe through the Country, and take up our malignant in their way, wee cannot pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise to keep the town but to lose our selves, seeing our whole strength consists but of Col. <hi>Pophams</hi> Regiment of Foot not compleat, and of Col. <hi>Fiennes,</hi> and Col. <hi>Coles</hi> Troopes of Horse.</p>
            <p>Wherefore we shall humbly propound the remedy, which is, that we may be enabled to raise, two other Regiments of foot, one under the command of Col. <hi>Fiennes,</hi> and the other under the command of And that we may have some supply of money from the Parliament; That these new raised Regiments together with Col. <hi>Pophams</hi> aforesaid Regiment, and Col. <hi>Fiennes</hi> Regiment of Horse be only destined for defence of this City and Country for twenty miles round about it, out of which territory of 20 miles compasse and this City, if they be left onely to us we hope to pay the said forces when as they are raised, we have written to his Excellency for two or three experienced Commanders to make Sergeant Majors, as many able Gunners, and a skillfull Engineer we beseech your Honour forward our desires, One advertisement more we shall trouble your Lordship withall; which is that our rich Merchants have shipped most of their Treasure, and the Ships lie off at Sea out of our command which seemes to threaten a storme at Land: If the Parliament could spare 2. or 3. good pinnaces to guard this haven and the Seaverne; that no Ships passe without licence, it would much secure these parts, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noy Wales, and we conceive the charge may be born by the toll upon
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:196872:8"/> all merchandize, which those malignants deserve to undergoe.</p>
            <p>The two Pinnaces sent by the Parliament to <hi>Milford</hi> Haven, are vessels of no force and their commanders of no activity that we heare of. And if we be trusted to take some accompt of their endeavours it may perchance quicken them, we have writ to his Excellency, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able us by his appointment to proceed with our Treacherous Conspirators, to the utmost extent of marshall Law; the wickednes of some of them deserving to be made an example of utmost severity, and without which, we shall incurre contempt and lie open to more practises, we beseech your Lordship bee the mediator of our humble desires, and make what use you please of them, to the close Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee we have revealed those weaknesses to your honour, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise wee desire to conceale knowing that a bare reputation in matters of War doth many times win the game. We are</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your honours humble<lb/> Servants.<lb/>
                  <list>
                     <item>Nathaniel Fiennes.</item>
                     <item>Alexander Popham.</item>
                     <item>Ch: Walker.</item>
                     <item>Joh. Seymoure.</item>
                     <item>Edw. Stephens.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
               <dateline>Bristoll, <date>20 March 1643.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:196872:9"/>
            <head>A Copie of a Letter written by my Lord Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, to the Lord SAY, concerning the setling of a sufficient Garison at BRISTOLL, according to the Propositions made by Colonell <hi>Fiennes</hi> to that purpose.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Understand there is a Committee of the House of Commons ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to consider of the establishing a Garison in the City of <hi>Bristoll.</hi> I am very glad of their care of it, being a place of so great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance. I desire your Lordship to acquaint the Committee with my resolution concerning the strength of that Garison, and entreate them that course may be taken for a sufficient maintenance for it.</p>
            <p>I Thinke it necessary that that Garison doe consist of those tvvo Regiments which Col. <hi>Fiennes</hi> hath already raised, and of that Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment under Col. <hi>Popham,</hi> of tvvo Troopes of Horse, and Captaine <hi>Olands</hi> company of Dragoons. This I thinke little enough both in respect of the importance of that place as being the Key of the West of <hi>England,</hi> and likewise because by these forces the Governour will bee able at all times to suppresle any that shall rise against us in those parts to assist our friends, as novv is done by Colonell <hi>Pophams</hi> Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>My Lord, I againe recommend this businesse to your care and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire you likevvise, that you vvill let my resolution herein be knowne to the Governour of <hi>Bristoll,</hi> and likewise to the Gentlemen of <hi>Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merset-shire, Glocester-shire,</hi> and <hi>Wilt-shire,</hi> that they may endeavour to settle some constant course for the maintenance of this Garison. My Lord I am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordships faithfull<lb/> Friend and Servant,<lb/> ESSEX.</signed>
               <lb/>
               <dateline>Thame, <date>Iune, 22.<lb/> 1643.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="ordinance">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:196872:9"/>
            <head>A Draught of the Ordinance presented to the House of Commons by the Le: <hi>Say,</hi> for the setling of a sufficient Garrison <hi>AT BRISTOLL,</hi> According to the Propositions made by Colonell <hi>Fiennes,</hi> and recommended unto his care by my Lord Generall, and the Gentlemen of Somer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>set and Gloucestershire.</head>
            <p>THe Lords and Commons taking into their serious conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, the great importance of the city of <hi>Bristoll,</hi> to the safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of this Kingdom, and the dangerous attempts that have been made against it by the late detestable Conspiracie, and the great Forces that were brought before it by Prince <hi>Rupert,</hi> into whose hands the Conspirators were prepared to have delivered the same; And that there is great danger that the like attempts may be made hereafter for the surprisall of it, if care be not taken for the preventing thereof,</p>
            <p>Do Order and Ordain, That there shall be a Garrison forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with raised by Colonell <hi>Fiennes,</hi> the Governour of the said City, consisting of Three Regiments of Foot, one of Twelve hundred men, and another of One thousand, another of Eight hundred men, and Two Troops of Horse, and One company of Dragoons, to be completely armed and furnished, and there kept and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in constant pay, for the defence of the said city and the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit thereof; And to be imployed for the defence of the city of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:196872:10"/>
               <hi>Bathe,</hi> and the adjacent counties of <hi>Somerset</hi> and <hi>Glocester,</hi> as oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion shall require.</p>
            <p>And that one of the said Regiments for the said Garrison, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisting of Twelve hundred men, shall be maintained by <hi>Barkley</hi> division, in the county of <hi>Gloucest,</hi> another of One thousand, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Colonels <hi>Pophams</hi> Regiment, with the Troops of Horse, and company of Dragoons, by that part of the Eastern division in the county of <hi>Somerset,</hi> which is next adjoyning to <hi>Bristoll</hi> and <hi>Bathe.</hi> And the third Regiment of Eight hundred men, together with other incident charges necessary for their safety, by the said cities of <hi>Bristoll</hi> and <hi>Bathe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And it is likewise Ordained, That there be Three Regiments more of Trained Bands, or Voluntiers, which upon Summons shall be drawn together from time to time; as often as need shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, for the defence of the said cities and counties adjacent; One of which Regiments of the Trained Bands, or Voluntiers, shall be raised out of <hi>Barkley</hi> division, in the county of <hi>Gloucest</hi>'; One other out of that part of the Eastern division of <hi>Somerset<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire,</hi> which is nearest <hi>Bristoll</hi> and <hi>Bathe;</hi> And the third, out of both the said cities.</p>
            <p>That for the better settlement of the Garrison in manner a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid, the Deputy-Lieutenants in the counties of <hi>Glouc</hi>' and <hi>Som<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rset,</hi> shall cause the Regiments of the Trained-Bands of their severall counties to be furnished again with Arms, those of <hi>Glocestershire</hi> being for the most part lost at <hi>Ciceter;</hi> And those of <hi>Somersetshire</hi> in the parts next <hi>Bristoll,</hi> being imployed in Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell <hi>Pophams</hi> Regiment, being one of the Three to be kept in constant pay as aforesaid.</p>
            <p>And that all the Moneys which shall be levyed out of <hi>B<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rkley</hi> division in <hi>Glouc</hi>', and out of that par<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Eastern division in <hi>Somersetshire</hi> which is ne<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t adjoyning to <hi>Bristoll</hi> and <hi>Bathe,</hi> and out of the cities of <hi>Bristoll</hi> and <hi>Bathe,</hi> by vertue of the severall Ordinances of both Houses for the weekly Assessments, the Twentieth part, and the Sequestrations of Delinquents Estates; shall be assigned for the use of the aforesaid Garrisons and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifications. And that the severall Committees who are appointed to receive or issue out Monies raised by these Ordinances in the said city of <hi>Bristoll,</hi> or the said counties adjacent shall pay and defray all the charges of the said Garrison and Fortifications, being valued and made known to them by the said Governour
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:196872:10"/> of <hi>Bristoll,</hi> out of the moneys so to be raised by the said Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces, before they do imploy any part thereof to any other use. And the Warrant and Receit of the said Colonell <hi>Fiennes</hi> Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the said city, shall be a sufficient discharge to the said Committees in that behalf. Provided alwayes, that if there shall not be a sufficient proportion for the uses aforesaid, raised out of the severall divisions and places before mentioned, that then it be made up out of the rest of the said counties respectively.</p>
            <p>And also that the surplusage (if any be) shall be imployed for the use of other parts of the adjacent counties, and for such other uses as shall be directed by both Houses of Parliament.</p>
            <p>And it is further Ordained by the Authority abovesaid, that aswell for the maintenance of the said Garrison, and the charges incident thereunto. As also, for the making and finishing of the Fortifications and Works in and about the said city of <hi>Bristoll,</hi> the said city of <hi>Bristoll</hi> shall pay, and is hereby rated and assessed to the Weekly sum of Four hundred pounds, to begin the First day of Iuly, 1643. And for the better performance thereof; and ease of the said city, It is Ordained by the Lords and Commons, That the Weekly sum of Fifty five pounds, formerly assessed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the said city by the late Ordinance of both Houses of Parl. for the Weekly Assessments towards the supply of the Army raised by Authority of Parliament, shall go and be accounted as part of the said Four-hundred pounds weekly for the maintenance of the said Garrison and Fortifications, and not otherwise to be required for the use of the said Army.</p>
            <p>It is further Ordained by the said Lords and Commons, That the said Weekly Assessment of Four hundred pounds shall be As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessed, rated, taxed, and levyed by Colonell <hi>Fiennes</hi> Governour of the said Town, Colonell <hi>Popham, Richard Aldsworth</hi> Major of the said city of <hi>Bristoll,</hi> Sergeant Major <hi>Iohn Clifton,</hi> Captain <hi>Richard Hippesley,</hi> Captain <hi>Thomas Hippesley,</hi> Mr. <hi>Luke Hodges,</hi> Mr. <hi>Henry Gribs,</hi> and Mr <hi>Iames Howell,</hi> who shall have like power and Authority, as other Committees have by the said se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Ordinances; And also have power and Authority to call unto them such of the most indifferent understanding, and suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient persons of every Parish within the said city of <hi>Bristoll</hi> as they shall think fit to their assistance; And shall rate and tax the said Weekly Assessment, charged by this Ordinance upon the Inhabitants, and the owners of goods or other Estate there, in such
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:196872:11"/> moderate and proportionable manner as they shall think fit, to and for the maintenance of the said Garrison and Fortifications; As also to have like power to levie the same, and to do all things necessary for the execution of this present Ordinance, as by the said former Ordinance for the Weekly Assessment is appointed; And that what shall be established in <hi>London</hi> by way of Excise or new Impost, upon Wines, Tobacco, or other Commodities, shall be likewise setled in <hi>Bristoll,</hi> towards the maintenance of the said Garrison and Fortifications (there.)</p>
            <p>And to the end the Trained Bands or Voluntiers above speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and the severall division and limits, out of which they shall be raised, may be the better able to perform the services, and discharge the payments before mentioned, It is further Ordained, That no Taxes or payments shalbe levyed or Assessed upon them, other then such as are or shall be Ordered by both Houses of Parliament.</p>
            <p>And it is also Ordained, That by the assent and Warrant of Colonell <hi>Fiennes</hi> the Governour of <hi>Bristoll,</hi> and Two or more of the Deputy-Lieutenants, or Committees of Parliament, resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in or n<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er the said divisions and no other, the Treasurers of the said Divisions and cities shall issue out monies for the use of the said Garrison and Fortifications; And that the said Trained-Bands or Voluntiers shall not be drawn away to other services, then what they are by this Ordinance assigned unto, without the like Warrant as aforesaid; And that by such Warrant they may be at any time drawn out into the said cities of <hi>Bristoll</hi> or <hi>Bath</hi> for the defence thereof.</p>
            <p>It is further Ordained, That the said Colonell <hi>Fiennes</hi> Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Bristoll</hi> shall have power to grant Commissions for Trained-Bands; As also for Bands of Voluntiers to be raised within the said cities; And that the same power which was gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Ordinance of Parliament to the Apprentices and others of <hi>London,</hi> that should be willing to undergo the like service, shall be extended to the said city of <hi>Bristoll.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for the securing of the River of <hi>Severn,</hi> and the Seas thereto adjoyning. It is Ordained, That the said Colonell <hi>Fienn<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> Governour of <hi>Bristoll,</hi> shall have power likewise to grant Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missions to any Merchants or others that will set out ships, to take any Welsh, Cornish, or Irish Rebells, or any Vessell that shall be imployed, to afford them or any of them any ayd or assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:196872:11"/> and to make prizes thereof, paying a third of all, that shall be taken, or such proportion as shall be thought fit to the use of the <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Lastly it is ordeyned, That Col. <hi>Nath: Fiennes,</hi> Governour of <hi>Bristoll, Alexander Popham,</hi> Capt. <hi>Iohn Fiennes,</hi> be added to the severall Committees of the weekly Assessement, the <hi>Twentieth Part,</hi> and the Committee for Sequestrations in the severall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Glocestershire and Sommersetshire, and in the Cities of <hi>Bristoll</hi> and <hi>Bath.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="approval">
            <head>An Approbation of the Ordinance presented to the House by the Lord <hi>Say,</hi> for the setling of the Garrison of Bristoll, by the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall Gentlemen of Berkly Devision in Glocestershire.</head>
            <p>VVEe whose names are under written, have seene the draught of an Ordinance of Parliament, for the setling of a Garrison in the City of <hi>Bristoll,</hi> and for the contribution and assistance of the adjacent Counties for the maintenance thereof, which we approve of, and hold very conduceable to the security both of the City and county, only we desire that a provision may be inserted, for the defraying of the charges of the Officers and Souldiers of the Trained-bands and Voluntiers, when they shall be called to do any service out of the severall Devisions out of the which they are raised, and that <hi>Berkly</hi> Castle may be furnished with a Garrison sufficient for the defence thereof out of the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rison of <hi>Bristoll;</hi> or upon the monies to bee raised out of <hi>Berkley</hi> Devision.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>John Seymour.</item>
                     <item>Edward Stephens.</item>
                     <item>Joh: Codrington.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="excerpt_of_letter">
            <head>An Extract out of a Letter from Col: <hi>Fiennes</hi> to my Lond Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, dated March 20. upon occasion of Sir <hi>Will. Wallers</hi> draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth Col: <hi>Essex's</hi> Regiment out of Bristoll.</head>
            <p>THe drawing forth of Col: <hi>Essex</hi> his whole Regiment may expose this City to a great deal of danger, there being not so much as one experienced Officer left among the Comparies that remain here, and the number and quality of the Common souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:196872:12"/> being much disproportionable to the necessity and importance of this place, as in a particular Letter which (with the rest of the Gentlemen of <hi>Sommersetshire,</hi> and <hi>Glouc.</hi> I writ to your Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency doth more fully appear:) And as I doubt not, but according to the constant care your Excellency hath had of this place, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swerable to the importance thereof, your Lordship will provide a person for the government thereof that may be fit to be intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted with so great a charge; so that your Excellency will also hold it fit that he may have such a command over the forces that shalbe thought fit for the defence of the place, as that he may be able to give a good accompt thereof. I earnestly expect a discharge from your Excellency of that trust, which at present is in my hands, that it may not be left at Random in no bodies hand at all: And that it may be reposed in a hand more fit and able for it; which is the humble desire of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Excellencies<lb/> most humble Servant.<lb/> Nath: Fiennes.</signed>
               <lb/>
               <dateline>Bristoll.<lb/>
                  <date>March 20. 1643.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="excerpt_of_letter">
            <head>An Extract of another Letter from Col: <hi>Fiennes</hi> to Col: <hi>Hamb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> dated <date>March. the 19th.</date>
            </head>
            <p>I Shall say onely this in generall, that if there be not some spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy course taken that more men may be brought to strengthen the Garrison, and some expert souldiers to command them, this Town in all probability will be lost, and all we that are in it. All that Sir <hi>Wil: VValler</hi> aleadgeth is this; that he being in the Field with a considerable body, doth stand between us and danger: but such a city as this should not be a noun adjective, nor depend upon the fortune or failing of a party in the field, the losse thereof be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of greater consequence then of the whole party in the field; I desire that either I may have leave to quitt the charge, (which was my earnest suit to Sir <hi>Wil: Waller</hi> that I might do) or that meanes might be afforded unto me to make it good; I shall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to any man that is a souldier, whether there be not need of 3000. men at least to be an ordinary Garrison for this Town with some Troops of horse and Dragoons. <hi>Bristoll</hi> is worth the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and yet in the judgement of any souldier not easie to be kept, though with a good strength of souldiers, but impossible to bee kept with a few; If that it be expected from me to give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:196872:12"/> of this place, I desire my straw may not be taken from me, and yet so great a tale of Brick be required at my hands.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I Am utterly discouraged in the employment I have here, because I do not see a way of subsistance for the forces that are here, for I doubt I can expect little money from</hi> London, <hi>and all the wayes whereby I got some heretofore out of Gloucestershire and Sommer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>setshire, will be stopped up and diverted towards the maintenance of Sir</hi> Wil: Wallers <hi>Army, and I shall be left to feed upon the bare stones, and yet Sir</hi> Wil: Waller <hi>at his first coming to this City, drew</hi> 2000 l. <hi>out of it, which if it might be allowed me till a course might be setled for the maintenance of this Garrison, I should have some probability of keeping up the horse and foot that I have, with a great deal of paines raised, without one penny allowance from</hi> London, <hi>but if all draw from me and none helpe me; I should desire that my Lo: Generall would command me to come to his Army with my Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of foot and horse, and that some body else may be put to keepe this Town, that can make it keep it selfe, for I confesse I cannot do it without assistance from the adjacent Counties, or from the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; That which will arise out of the Delinquents estates, will not be considerable; there are not many of any estate, that were in the Conspiracy, and they have found meanes to conceale the greatest part of their estates; and what is visible will bee little more then what is sufficient to pay their debters; And I perceive the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment intendeth to allow the payment of debts out of their estates, (which is just that it should be done, so there be care that the State be not deceived by pretended debts, or such as are contracted since the Conspiracy.) My Lord, I cannot long subsist in this employment un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse that there be a course t<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> help me with monies, or that power be given me to help my self in this City and the adjacent parts.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordships most obedient<lb/> Son, Nath: Fiennes.</signed>
               <lb/>
               <dateline>Bristol. <date>Apr. 22.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="excerpt_of_letter">
            <head>An Extract of a Letter written from Col: <hi>Fiennes</hi> to the Lord <hi>Say</hi> his Father, <date>
                  <hi>May, 12. 1643.</hi>
               </date>
            </head>
            <p>I Have layed out here, neer 9000. l. since I came to this Town, and I never yet had above 4000 l. from the Parliament; as your
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:196872:13"/> Lordship best knows, all the rest I have got up my selfe with great deal of trouble for the preservation of this City, which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it had undoubtedly fallen into the hands of the enemy.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="excerpt_of_letter">
            <head>An Extract of a Letter from Col: <hi>Fiennes</hi> to the Lord <hi>Say</hi> his Father, dated <date>
                  <hi>May 13, 1643.</hi>
               </date>
            </head>
            <p>I Am in that extremity for want of money, that I know not what to do, and all the springs which formerly afforded me sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, are dryed up, for Sir <hi>Wil: Waller</hi> expecteth all out of the counties, and the City will not continue their weekly contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion any longer: If the Propositions of joyning a certain Circuit in Sommersetshire and Glocestershire to this Towne, as to the maintenance of this Garrison with money, and men upon occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, might be granted; I should hope by the grace of God to give a good accompt of this City and the adjacent parts; And I am confident there is no objection against them, but what ariseth out of particular respects to the prejudice of the publick interest, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse those Propositions may be admitted, or a continuall supply granted from <hi>London,</hi> (which I cannot expect:) all that I build here is without a foundation, and must needs fall to the ground, and this Town into the hands of the enemy.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="excerpt_of_letter">
            <head>An Extract out of a Letter from Col: <hi>Fiennes</hi> to my Lord <hi>Say</hi> his Father, <date>
                  <hi>June 9: 1643.</hi>
               </date>
            </head>
            <p>THe Lord deliver me from the condition wherein I am, that I should have the charge of a Town of such importance as this is upon me, &amp; neither have men halfe enough to maintain it, nor mony to maintain those men I have, nor means afforded me to raise any mony, I beseech your Lordship dispatch unto me by order of the House, a power to rate Malignants and Neutralls at the 20th. part of their estate; If I had but this I might be able to raise some monies (although not sufficient) for the Garrison, unlesse the adjacent counties come in to our assistance; and it is all the reason in the world that Glocestershire should maintaine one Regiment in this City, Sommerset, another, and the City, with the help of Wiltshire another; if some such course were settled, I should have lesse recourse to supplies from <hi>London;</hi> till then I must, or this Town must be lost, and all that is in it, and all that depend upon it, which will not so soone be <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ed againe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="excerpt_of_letter">
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:196872:13"/>
            <head>An Extract of another Letter written to the Lord Say, <date>June 17. 1643.</date>
            </head>
            <p>MY Lord I much wonder that any should conceive the estates of the Conspirators any thing consideable, in respect of the great charge I am constantly at, being to pay 1500 foot, a Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Horse, and a company of Dragoones, and a hundred Gunners, besides workmen upon the Fortifications; so that I have beene sometimes at 1300. l. sometimes at 1200. l. seldome under 1000. l. a weeke; and I shall never make 3000. l. from the beginning to the end out of the Conspirators estates, there being never a rich man amongst them; and their Creditors claiming and carrying away the greatest part of what is not abroad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed away, or so concealed that I cannot find it out; and I can assure your Lordship I have already received and spent the most of what I am to expect that way, otherwise I had not beene able to have subsisted halfe this time: It were folly in me to conceale that which will prove the truth, if out of the conceipt of the riches of <hi>Bristoll</hi> (which since the stop of trade, and many Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants withdrawing their estates, is much otherwise then is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by some) I am left to maintaine this Garrison, without assistance from the Countries or from some other way, I shall not be able to keepe my men together for a fortnight: for my part I shall desire to be discharged of the trust, unlesse I may have means to discharge it with honour to my selfe, and safety to the City and countries adjacent; I am confident they are their owne greatest enemies that oppose my propositions for the setling this Garrison, and that if they have their wils, they will quickly see this City fall into the enemies hands, and so have a perpetuall yoke, to the Counties of <hi>Gloucester</hi> and <hi>Sommerset;</hi> I shall muster up all the patience that is in me, but I cannot hold out long in that manner that I have done; Sir <hi>William Waller</hi> hath now a good strength about him, especially of Horse, and for ought that I see the enemy will fight with him, I must confesse I doubt the successe, unlesse it come extraordinarily from God, as formerly it hath done.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="excerpt_of_letter">
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:196872:14"/>
            <head>Another Extract of a Letter of <date>Iune 24.</date>
            </head>
            <p>MY Lord I have ever since I came to this City, beene in a trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blesome and very oft in a dangerous condition, but I am like to be put to it now more then ever, and had I not had experience of Gods mercy to me in times of streights, my faith would wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigh faile me. I will not write the particulars whereon I ground this apprehension of my condition, not knowing into what hands this Letter may come, but only in generall I will say thus much, That happily the support that this City and all the rest seemes to relye on (which is Sir <hi>William Wallers</hi> army) may faile us, but God will never faile us. At the last Rendesvouz that Sir <hi>William Waller</hi> had of his horse, there appeared betweene two and three thousand horse, a brave body of horse, &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="excerpt_of_letter">
            <head>Another Extract of a Letter of <date>July 8. 1643.</date> Sent by the same Col. <hi>Fines</hi> to my Lord <hi>Say</hi> his Father.</head>
            <p>I Beseech your Lordship to cause my Ordinance for the setling of a garrison at <hi>Bristoll</hi> to bee dispatched; me thinks there should be no stop of it now that I have sent an approbation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, under the hands of all those considerable Gentlemen that live in those parts whereon the burthen is principally to lye; your Lordship cannot imagine what difficulties I am put upon for want of that Ordinance, and if God had not given my Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers and Officers a great deale of patience, we must needs have fallen all to pieces by this time; and this day I am in as great ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity as ever, and do live every day but from hand to mouth. I am sure all my Propositions have no other aime but the publick good. I beseech your Lordship againe to hasten the dispatch of that Ordinance which is in hand, &amp; in the mean time being a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry beggar, I must still beg for supplyes of money.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A Letter written by Sir <hi>W. Waller</hi> and Sir <hi>Arthur Haslerigge</hi> to Mr: <hi>John Ashe,</hi> to hasten forces out of <hi>Bristol</hi> unto them, Whereupon 1200 was sent.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Good Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SUre you think we have both a lame and a patient enemy, that will be knockt and stay till we be ready to answer his returne.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:196872:14"/> We expected Col. <hi>Fines</hi> Regiment this day, and now I heare that he appointed that Sir <hi>John Seymors</hi> men should not come to <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stoll</hi> before Monday, and then we are to expect ours. Upon Tuse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day we think the Enemy will fall on this night, if not, to morrow morning; and if so, what good will this Regiment do <hi>Bristoll,</hi> if we perish. It is a wonder to me to see our friends delay helpe when there in safety; and I am confident, Honour is wrapt up in our successe. It is said your Captains have not yet cast lots who shall come forth; I thought they would have petitioned for the imployment. We shall be happy in Col. <hi>Pophams</hi> Regiment, and Col. <hi>Fines</hi> also; surely a small guard will keep under the Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, we being so neare. Let not the west of <hi>England</hi> be lost for a little monies, neither send your supplies too late. There is a time which wise-men do not let slippe. It is strange to me, that these Forces have not long since been drawne out. What forces you send us, let us have them with all speed. It grieves our hearts you are no more sensible of our present condition, and the nearnesse and strength of the Enemy. We have done our duties, the Lord direct you. We are</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Servants,<lb/>
                  <list>
                     <item>William Waller.</item>
                     <item>Art. Hasilrige.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
               <lb/>
               <dateline>
                  <date>July 1. 1643.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="document">
            <head>A Copie of the Result of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Warre held by the Enemies, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Assaulting of the City of <hi>Bristoll,</hi> found in Collonel <hi>Bucks</hi> pocket that was there staine, with divers other Officers and Gentlemen of qualitie.</head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>At the Councell of Warre held at <hi>Knowle,</hi> neare <hi>Bristoll,</hi> Somerset. <date>the five and twentieth day of July, 1643</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>Their Highnesse Prince <hi>Rupert,</hi> and Prince <hi>Maurice. Present.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Earle of Carnarvon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir</hi> John Biron.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Serjeant Major Generall</hi> Wagstaffe.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir</hi> Richard Cave.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir</hi> William Ogle.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir</hi> Richard Slanning.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Collonell</hi> Buck.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Collonell</hi> Basset.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lieutenant Col.</hi> Ashtley.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lieutenant Col.</hi> Oneale.</item>
            </list>
            <div type="question">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:196872:15"/>
               <head>Question.</head>
               <p>VVHether it be best to assault, or approach the City of <hi>Bristoll?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="resolution">
               <head>Resolution.</head>
               <p>It is resolved by the whole Councell of Warre for divers reasons, that it shall be assaulted by both the Armies on all sides, according to the best skill and discretion of the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in chiefe that are to fall on.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="orders">
               <head>Orders.</head>
               <p>It is ordered that the houre appointed for them to fall on, shall be to morrow morning, just at the breake of day: The word for the Souldiers to be <hi>Oxford;</hi> and the signe betweene the two Armies, whereby to know each other, to be greene colours, either bowes, or such like, and that every Officer and Souldier be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any band or hand-cherchiefe about his neck.</p>
               <p>That the Collonels of the severall Brigads as soone as they shall have entred the Enemies Workes, shall presently appoint some to throw downe the Brest-workes, and fill up the ditches in severall places where they enter, or other places more convenient for the entrance of our Horse (if occasion require.)</p>
               <p>That the Commanders in Chiefe of the severall Brigads doe agree between themselves in what manner <hi>Ratcliffe</hi> Church shal be possessed, and if possessed, how maintained; and that they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point certaine Officers for that purpose.</p>
               <p>That the Generall of the Ordnance give speciall order, that all the Souldiers be furnished with all kind of Amunition, and that severall Officers be by him appointed to attend the severall Brigads with Amunition during the Assault, as also that the Artil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary, and the Officers thereto belonging, be ordered to be readie upon all Commands.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <closer>
               <signed>Ex. per Geo. Trym. Secr.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>